In the last video, I talked about
the fact that we will mainly model with diagrams.
And I also mentioned that these
will usually be graph structures somehow.
You know graphs,
at least intuitively.
Perhaps you have also looked
at them more formally in
school mathematics
lessons, for example.
First of all, graphs
are clearly net-like structures,
consisting of nodes and edges,
which together form a context.
There are different
kinds of graphs.
Here is
just an example.
This one is
directed, insofar as
the edges each have an end,
which is marked by an arrow.
There are also graphs where this is
irrelevant, where you just have the connection
without specifying
a particular direction.
There is the possibility,
which is not realized here,
that there are multiple edges
between the same two nodes.
Because maybe there are supposed to be different paths,
or maybe an outward path and a return path.
That does not
occur here now.
But that
is mathematically allowed.
We can have node
labels and edge labels.
Here we have the nodes labeled with
numbers and the edges labeled with letters.
Both are optional in
general or could be designed differently.
Graphs can, in
principle, be mathematically infinite.
Of course, we will generally be dealing
with finite graphs rather than infinite ones, because
our models are
supposed to be finite.
So, there are
different varieties of graphs.
But they all have
this basic feature in common,
the idea of expressing facts
by nodes and intermittent edges.
And not surprisingly, graphs can
be used well for modeling.
On the one hand, conceivably for
static modeling, when the goal is
to describe the
nature of a system.
Then, for example, the nodes could
stand for individual components of the
system, and the relationships between these components
could then be represented by the edges.
Or for dynamic
modeling, one could imagine
that the nodes
are individual states.
So in each case, the expression of
the entirety of the system at a concrete
time would be such a state (instead
of the entire graph representing the state).
And the edges would then be
transitions between individual states of the system.
So descriptive, for example, of
how the system evolves over time.
Or under which conditions, which
might be written on these edges,
the system makes a state transition
from one specific expression to another.
That first in general for
the role that graphs might have.
Then I'm going to do an
example now, which may seem a
little artificial, a little far-fetched,
especially as a modeling example.
It's also not related to computer science,
so it's not a computer science system.
And strictly speaking,
you could also say:
It's just
a little puzzle.
A little puzzle that some
of you may already know.
Possibly from the computer science
pre-course, similar things are done there.
Maybe just from other contexts,
even if it's from school.
I'm doing it here because it allows me
in a very naive way to show a
little bit of
this abstraction process.
And just finding notation for a concrete
problem, and then representing that as a graph.
So bringing graphs into play
to ultimately solve that problem.
So you can say it
doesn't involve much modeling.
But about the transition graphs, the
one that's going to occur here now,
that's already alluding to
something that we're going to use later.
Both with Petri nets
and with UML state diagrams.
That's why I'm doing this example,
not because it's a realistic
modeling
problem now.
So, what
is the problem?
Wolf-goat-cabbage, it
says right here.
So, we have a
puzzle world like that.
There's the farmer who
wants to cross a river.
He has these three things, or
animals (wolf, goat, and cabbage), with him.
He wants to cross
the river, as I said.
There is a
boat for this purpose.
But there is only room
for two in the boat.
So for the farmer himself (because the other
three, neither wolf nor goat nor cabbage, can
row themselves; therefore the farmer must always
go with them) and always only one of his possessions.
So, in particular, not
even two of these possessions.
And the problem now is
that the goat would like
to eat the cabbage, and the
wolf would like to eat the goat.
So if the farmer crosses the river
with the cabbage, then the wolf and
the goat would be alone and
the wolf would eat the goat.
And since only the farmer can row,
and he can cross the river either
alone or with an animal or the
cabbage head, now the question would be:
Is it possible for
the farmer to cross the
river without losing
one of his possessions?
What might one want
to model here, anyway?
Well, for example, the actors that
occur here, that make up the system.
Relationships between
the actors.
Maybe start state and goal state,
and of course the behavior, the action.
What
can happen.
How states can evolve, and how
to get from start to finish, perhaps.
So, not start and finish, just
left and right of the river.
But
actually, as start:
The farmer is on
one side with his property.
And
finish:
The farmer is on the
other side with all his possessions.
So in a sense, of
course, it's not necessarily a modeling
problem, but rather a way to get
more familiar with graphs again in an example.
That's at least how
I'm going to use it.
So,
naively:
First,
static model.
Who are the
actors and objects involved?
Exactly
these four.
There is still little structure
here, or no structure at all.
It's just a set of four
elements, not really a graph either.
Naively, it is also a graph, which just
consists of four nodes and no edges at all.
But you wouldn't really call that a graph
now, because you don't have a network structure.
So that could certainly be
better, more informative in particular.
You could represent the
relationships between the individual actors/objects.
So, let's add a
little bit of structure.
You can
ask yourself:
What are the
relationships that are relevant?
And well, from the puzzle description, there
are two relationships in particular that are conceivable.
On the one hand, the
possession relationship, so:
The farmer has
wolf, goat, and cabbage.
So here is "owns", even though
"owns" was not explicitly mentioned in the puzzle text.
There was something about "has with him" and
"shall therefore take with him across the river".
That is, so to
speak, the one relationship.
And then there
are these relationships,
these eating relationships, which are obviously
also somehow relevant to the puzzle.
We need to know who is
eating whom, so that we can
decide which situations are
safe and which are not.
So,
we know:
Wolf
eats goat.
Goat
eats cabbage.
We know, fortunately, that the
wolf would not eat the farmer.
Not even if he was
alone in the boat with him.
And we also know that
the wolf doesn't eat the cabbage.
Although it says "eats" and "eats", it is
not directly true that the wolf eats the cabbage.
This is also important, otherwise
we could not solve the riddle.
Now, you
might ask yourself:
Why should I
do this at all?
To capture
the puzzle.
But perhaps one of the purposes of
modeling here might be to then be
able to describe situations to which the
solution to this problem would be transferable.
So you would have
other animals, other actors,
but with analogous or
only slightly different feeding relationships.
One could
then ask oneself:
How analogous are
the two situations?
For example, can a solution to this
problem be transferred to a similar problem?
Then it is not so important which picture
is here, but the relations are the relevant thing.
And that's why it might be
interesting to model and capture that here.
That would be
the static side.
After all, a bit of somehow
visualizing the verbal text from the problem description.
The dynamic part
is certainly more interesting.
So we have to
talk about the individual situations.
And it makes sense to
first show the initial situation
before crossing
the river.
Again, first naively
as a picture.
Here in the middle is
the river, here is the boat.
The problem description
does not say that
the boat is at the beginning
on the left side of the river.
But if the puzzle should be
solvable at all, it is certainly
understandable that the boat should be
at the beginning where the farmer is.
So we decided to
show that here as well.
And we also know that
all four actors are on the
same side at the beginning,
namely where the boat is.
So that the puzzle can be
solved in a meaningful way at all.
What is
the target situation?
Well, it
looks like this.
The river is
still there, of course.
But all four actors, and also the boat,
are, at the end, on the right side.
Strictly speaking, the
same applies here:
The problem description does not require that the
boat is on the right at the end.
The problem description would not
care where the boat is.
So, even a situation where
these four actors are on the
right, but the boat is on the
left, would be a solution to the problem.
But with a little bit of
thinking, you come up with this:
That can't
happen at all.
So such a situation
will not be achievable.
That's why
we can say:
This has to be the
goal; there is no other way.
Also, that these three actors/objects end up
on the right side is
not explicitly in the problem
description (in the puzzle text).
But it said that the farmer has them
with him and would like to cross the river.
And from this we conclude
that he naturally wants to
arrive with his three possessions on
the right side of the river.
Therefore, it is justified
to consider that as the
only target
situation to be reached.
So those would
be the two situations.
That would still be
static modeling in a sense.
And dynamic would be,
now, if we deal with
how we can get back
and forth between the situations.
After all,
we can't say:
"We get from
here to there."
Obviously,
we can't.
That's not legal,
just to say:
Yes, the four actors
cross the river by boat.
Then we wouldn't
have captured the problem.
So instead, we have
to describe more fine-grained, so
to speak, individual transitions
that are really allowed.
For example,
we might say:
In the first step, let the farmer cross
the river with the wolf in the boat.
That's what the arrows
here are supposed to indicate.
What will
happen then?
Hopefully, it will
look like this afterwards.
The first
step is over.
We would now want to
think about the second step.
So:
What could the farmer do next
after he brings the wolf over there?
He can't do anything, because
the second step happens immediately:
Namely, the goat
eats the cabbage.
This eating
happens immediately,
without any possibility of the
farmer intervening somehow through action.
This can also be read from the
riddle text, if you read it generously, that
this eating happens in such a
way that the farmer cannot prevent it.
He can't call
over and say:
"Leave
it."
Then the puzzle would be uninteresting if
he could stop the goat from a distance.
He can only do that if he
is where the goat and the cabbage are.
Our real goal, of course,
is to write this down more
clearly now, instead of
always taking pictures like this.
For that, we want
to use graphs right away.
And of course, we do that just
to have a notation that goes beyond
these pictures that have to
be painted over and over again.
For this, we distinguish, in modeling
and ultimately also in programming (so also
in other lectures you will
encounter these terms): syntax and semantics.
So the syntax, the symbols, the
forms (in our case often diagrams),
which one may use for
the representation of the model.
So in this naive example just
now, of course, these would be
the pictures that we saw: the blue area
for the river, the picture of the goat, etc.
And the semantics would be what
is behind these diagrams, shapes, symbols.
So the blue area
is actually the river.
It separates
the two sides.
It has some effect,
because, for example, the river
prevents the farmer from influencing what's
on the other side, and so on.
And the arrows that we
have seen here are also symbols.
They are there to express the
actual action, the step of crossing.
That would be the
semantics of these arrows, etc.
Here, of course, it was all very intuitive,
so one might not even consider it
necessary to work out
what syntax and semantics are.
But in general,
of course, it is.
It's not
always so clear.
So for a syntax there
is not always a corresponding semantics.
In our example, on the one hand, we
can say that the semantics is quite vague.
On the other hand, the problem
is so simple that just by looking
at it, you have an
idea of what's going on.
In general, of course, one
would want to capture that somehow.
What is desirable
in general is
that this meaning of symbols
and shapes is very precise.
So that different modelers,
or different consumers of the
model, can understand that respectively,
and in the same way.
For this, a
common language/notation is
useful, common visual description
forms to avoid misunderstandings.
And indeed, graphs
form such a
possible language/notation
for many contexts.
That is why they form the basis
for many modeling techniques designed in graph form.
Thereby, of course, such a definition
can happen exactly for a concrete example.
So: We model
this wolf-goat-cabbage-head problem,
and for it, we record what
the notation and symbols should be.
It is even
more useful in practice
if one can describe in a
unified way in the modeling approach.
Petri nets will
be something like that.
This will be a modeling approach
that has a fixed syntax and semantics.
So they are independent of the
specific system that one is modeling.
This can be explained in general terms, for
example, be described in a book, and then quite
different problems, systems, models can be
followed and described with this approach.
Then, syntax and semantics
are unified across multiple models.
Otherwise, again
as a reminder:
Of course, graphs are not
the only way to create uniformity.
Mathematics does
that, too.
So with textual formulas, with logic,
you can of course specify things, model
things, and also have
a common formal basis.
But here we will
mainly work with graphs.
Now it didn't always
look like a graph.
But, of course,
our previous representation
for this problem
also hides graphs.
So, let's go back
to the static modeling.
There, we had this picture,
with the arrows in between.
That was a
graph, of course.
So these
relationships between the farmer,
the wolf, the goat, and the cabbage, we
could represent with this graph.
The edges are labeled with
the relationships between the nodes, which
are labeled with the
names of the actors.
This is simply the same picture as
the one here, only now these photos are replaced with symbols.
It's totally obvious and clear,
just a little more abstract.
And of course, here again, for example:
there is no transition from wolf to cabbage with "eats".
That expresses the
same fact as before.
That would be
for static modeling.
What about
the dynamic modeling?
There, I had
also already said:
Then, you would consider the nodes as
states and the edges as transitions between them.
So a bit like the step from
here to here suggested by the arrows.
You would then actually have
two explicit nodes in the
graph, and this arrow would
go from state to state.
Classical representatives of this, that
is, using graphs for dynamic modeling,
are so-called
flat state diagrams.
They are often also
called transition systems.
They are often
just called state diagrams.
In the lecture, I always
explicitly say "flat statecharts" until
we get
to UML statecharts.
To make
the difference
clear, namely that UML statecharts
are not flat, in a sense.
They have more structure than
just nodes and edges in between.
That's why, whenever we
have just this node-edge
structure, I'll talk
about flat statecharts.
I hope that's how
it's uniformly handled in the
exercise task collection
by now, too.
What is such
a flat state diagram?
It's actually just a
directed graph, possibly edge-labeled.
So the
nodes are states.
They'll usually have some
name, some description, some label.
The graph is supposed to be directed, in
the sense that there are arrows in between.
Even though this was
still static modeling here.
But the edges that we
have are supposed to be directed.
They could
also be labeled.
For example, at the transitions,
it could somehow say which
action is responsible
for changing the state.
But that
could be optional.
Maybe it's enough to have the
states as a set of nodes.
And the transitions
have to be there,
but they don't have to be
labeled extra, with some label on them.
Also, you usually want
to highlight a start state,
usually with
an incoming arrowhead.
And sometimes we also designate
one or more distinguished end states.
Then, one wants to express from where to where
one would like to go in the state diagram.
Let's do that
for our little problem.
So, a flat state diagram
for our wolf-goat-cabbage problem.
Then we definitely
have our starting state.
That's a little bit
of small print here.
I hope you
can still follow this,
even though I'm not
developing this largely on the whiteboard now.
What is meant here in each case (this is
also written down again on a slide in a moment):
The state, which is
abbreviated by the four actors.
And here there is a
vertical line, which represents the river.
So what this first state
is supposed to symbolize here:
Farmer, wolf, goat, cabbage
are left of the river.
This is one
possible state, and
it's the starting state (that's
why it's distinguished by this arrowhead).
And then
you can think:
What
can happen?
We had noted earlier this one
transition where we come from just
this situation (which we also just identified
as the start state) to this state.
That would
be the state:
Vertical line, goat and cabbage on the left of
it, farmer and wolf on the right of it.
So that would
be written down as ZK|FW.
Do we have that
in our graph as well?
Yes, so
here first:
We also have
a target state.
But we don't know
how to get there yet.
Somehow we have
to take steps.
What could be
the first step?
For example, the farmer could
drive the goat across the river.
Right now, this is not
the condition I just showed you.
This would be the condition that
we identified earlier as the problem.
Where the farmer crosses
the river with the wolf.
Then we would
have that condition.
But that's an immediate failure state because
then the goat will eat the cabbage.
And before that, in any order,
I may have tried other things here.
So here I don't have to try anything
else, but I had decided here for example:
Yes, let the farmer cross
the river with the goat.
That's not a failure state, because
the wolf won't eat the cabbage.
That would
be a possibility.
And then you
could think about:
What can
happen next?
Now
here came:
The farmer
could go back.
Then the goat
would be left alone.
The farmer could then cross
the river with the wolf.
So for each of these arrows, for the
transitions, there is a possible step behind it.
There are also
such observations as:
Except when you've
made a step that
leads to a failure, you
can always turn steps around.
Then there are
two arrows now.
The farmer can cross the river with
the goat, then he would be here.
Then this would
be the state.
But it also works
the other way around.
That is, everywhere we have an
arrow, we can turn it around.
Except for the failure states, because
you can't get out of them.
They are fatal, literally fatal
to any of the possessions.
Now, as I
said, I don't really
want to explain or develop
this step by step here now.
But you can, by trial
and error and following all
the possibilities, complete this graph and
eventually come to a complete picture.
This is
not yet complete.
What's still
missing here?
We have all these double
transitions. We have failure states.
From the success state, of
course, you can make a stupid
mistake and still spoil
it, so to speak.
That's probably not what the
farmer is going to want.
So, we
would probably say:
When the farmer reaches this
state, he lets it go.
And doesn't move
around anymore.
But purely formally,
you could say:
You can still go from the
success state to the failure state.
But something is
still missing here.
And that's because, you
can think about that:
Actually, the graph
has to be symmetric.
It's completely arbitrary to say that
the farmer wants to go from left to right.
You could just as well have said that the farmer is on
the right at the beginning and wants to go to the left.
So then you would have
had to develop this graph
to start here
and end here.
And for that, however, the
graph must be completely symmetrical.
So you have to be able
to tilt it from top to bottom.
And then transitions are missing,
as you can see here.
These transitions
are still missing.
Then the graph
is both left-right symmetric,
because it is mirrored at this axis, and you
can obviously also mirror it from top to bottom.
Then it does not look exactly symmetrical
when painted on, but in fact it is.
So, if you only capture the connections
and not exactly how the arrows were painted.
Namely, these two transitions correspond to the transitions
from here to here and here to here.
Then the graph
is indeed symmetrical.
This is ultimately due to the
fact that intuitively one could reverse
the feeding relationships and swap
the roles of wolf and cabbage.
Then the symmetry is
according to this axis.
And the symmetry according to
this axis is that it
wouldn't really matter whether you want left to
right or right to left as a farmer.
The symmetry in terms
of beginning and end.
So, the
notation here was:
The vertical line represents
the river; on the
left and on the right are
the actors, whose order doesn't matter.
So, I would not make a
difference between the states WKFZ and KWFZ.
Therefore, just always sort the
letters in a certain consistent way.
Because it wouldn't matter in which order they
are standing there on one side of the river.
I don't specify
the boat at all.
It appears in the picture before, but
actually I don't need to specify it,
because it will always be
where the farmer is anyway.
That's why it doesn't show
up in the notation anymore.
I had not
labelled the transitions here.
Of course, you could have labelled them
by always writing the action on them.
For
example:
"The farmer brings the
goat across the river."
Think up some name
for it, a short
label, and write that
on the corresponding arrows.
I didn't do that
here now for clarity.
I had used the
angular red states for failures.
So, for example, when
the goat eats the cabbage.
Such actions have priority over
crossings in a certain sense, which
is why there are no
return edges from failure nodes.
I can't reverse this arrow here,
because in that case it's a failure.
The goat eats the
cabbage and then nothing works.
That's why edges leading out
of such states were omitted.
Because they are not allowed according
to the semantics of the problem.
And this double-blue
ellipse, I had already
marked as the desired target
state at the very beginning.
So in a certain way, you
could say here, this is the syntax/semantics
description for
this graph.
In general, labels like
that are not redundant.
This is really a
choice I made here.
Simply so that the
representation doesn't get more complicated.
In general, it
can already be
very important to have the
labels on the edges as well.
Also, the colors could be seen
as separate labels in the end.
The fact that a node is red
or blue could also be seen as:
This is yet another label
that is on the node.
What else can be
seen on the concrete graph?
There are several paths from the
start state to the target state.
A solution to the problem
would be exactly one path through
this graph that
somehow follows the arrows.
Just because of this part of the graph,
where one could always follow the arrows here,
it turns out that there are infinitely
many solutions, which also become arbitrarily long.
If the farmer somehow always carries out
so to speak senseless actions in this circle,
before he then decides to go
truly in the direction of the goal.
From this, you can see that although it is
a finite graph, it contains infinitely many paths.
In fact, there are infinitely
many, arbitrarily long, successful paths.
The two shortest ones
contain seven transitions each, and
these are the interesting ones
for the solution of the problem.
Already this graph has
not been really small now.
But for interesting actual
systems, such flat state diagrams
can get amazingly large very
quickly, even for relatively simple systems.
This is
called state explosion.
It simply means that even with
just a few ingredients, there are still
a lot of possible
states, and correspondingly complicated graphs.
And you can't really
avoid that with flat state
diagrams, because they just represent
all states and all transitions explicitly.
This will later be a motivation for
the already mentioned UML state diagrams, which
have extra structure, and therefore can
avoid this explosion to some extent.
In our problem, sometimes
in other problems as well,
one can exploit symmetry, for instance, to get a
little bit on top of the state explosion problem.
In general, you just
need more powerful modeling tools.
But let's just work
with graphs for now.